Carl Bohnen
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Carl Bohnen papers
1888-1977
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Bohnen, Carl
2.8 linear feet
The papers of portrait painter Carl Bohnen date from 1888-1977, and measure 2.8 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical materials; correspondence among family, clients, and colleagues; scattered business records; a sketchbook and loose sketches; miscellaneous notes and writings; three scrapbooks of clippings and additional printed materials. Photographs are of Bohnen, family members, colleagues, views of Paris in the late 1920s, Native American models, portrait clients, and artwork.
Provenance
The Carl Bohnen papers were donated in 1978 by the artist's daughter-in-law, Dorothy Clark Bohnen, and his granddaughter, Blythe Bohnen.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Charles "Carl" Bohnen was born in October 1872 (according to the U.S. Census) in Erie, Pennsylvania, to Nicholas and Marie Jochin Bohnen, who had emigrated from Germany. The family moved to Meyer's Grove, Minnesota in the following year.
Carl Bohnen graduated from St. John's University at Collegeville, Minnesota in 1892, earning a diploma in "Bookkeeping and Penmanship." Soon afterwards, he met Jake Hohman who employed him in a business involving drawing portraits from photographs. In 1896, Bohnen established a studio in St. Paul, Minnesota, where he continued creating portraits from photographs. During this time, he met Charlotte Johnson, whom he married in 1898.
Bohnen moved his studio in 1902 and began painting portraits from life. Paul Manship's family were neighbors of the Bohnens at Bald Eagle Lake near St. Paul, Minnesota. Bohnen studied at the Minnesota School of Fine Arts in exchange for cleaning up the classrooms. He later made space available to Manship in his studio.
In 1904, Bohnen completed studies at the St. Paul Art Institute. He also did commercial work, including doing portraits of sports figures for the St. Paul Pioneer Press and Dispatch. Through his newspaper connections, he did portraits of many other celebrities, later selling reproductions of these artworks. Eventually, he was hired as a portrait painter by a variety of prominent sitters, including R. A. Jackson, a railroad executive in St. Paul. An exhibition of Bohnen's portraits organized by Jackson resulted in additional commissions.
Through R. A. Jackson, several lumber millionaires helped finance a European trip for the Bohnen family in 1914. Bohnen studied at the Koenigliche Kunst Academie in Munich under Carl Von Marr and Angelo Jank, and established a studio in that city. Travel constraints resulting from the onset of World War I caused the family to remain in Munich for three years. During this time, Bohnen was a member of the American Artist Club that included E. Martin Hennings, Louis Grell, and Emil Frei.
Bohnen and his family returned to St. Paul, Minnesota in May 1918, where he established a studio. He moved to Chicago in the following year, opening a studio in the Fine Arts building where he remained until the 1930s. Bohnen created thousands of portraits primarily of notable people including Edward the Prince of Wales, Ethel Barrymore, Enrico Caruso, Helen Hayes, Charles Lindbergh, Douglas MacArthur, John McCormack, Cardinal Mundelein, and Lawrence Tibbett.
In 1928, Bohnen established a studio in Paris and worked there sporadically through 1933. In 1933, he returned to St. Paul, Minnesota, setting up his studio in the Ryan Hotel. In 1944, he retired to live in Los Angeles, California, with his son, actor Roman Bohnen. After his son's sudden death in 1949, Bohnen lived with his other son, Arthur, in Chicago.
Carl Bohnen died on December 31, 1951 in Willmette, Illinois.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of portrait painter Carl Bohnen date from 1888-1977, and measure 2.8 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical materials; correspondence among family, clients, and colleagues; scattered business records; a sketchbook and loose sketches; miscellaneous notes and writings; three scrapbooks of clippings and additional printed materials. Photographs are of Bohnen, family members, colleagues, views of Paris in the late 1920s, Native American models, portrait clients, and artwork.
Biographical material includes miscellaneous Bohnen family histories and chronologies of Bohnen's career, Bohnen's marriage certificate, school transcripts, and copies of his burial certificate.
Family correspondence consists of letters exchanged between Bohnen, his wife, siblings, and children. General correspondence is with colleagues including Carl Von Marr, and portrait clients including Constance Collier, John Erskine, Edna Ferber, and Frank B. Kellogg. The letters are often emotional and illustrate occasionally volatile relationships between Bohnen, his clients, and his children. Also included are condolence letters received by the family following Bohnen's death.
Business records include a contract for financial backing of artistic activities, insurance records, miscellaneous receipts, and a file concerning the elderly Bohnen's injuries on an American Airlines flight bringing him from California to live with his son in Chicago.
Artwork found within the papers consists of a sketchbook, miscellaneous sketches, hand-lettered signs for Bohnen's portrait business, etchings by Bohnen and others, a bronze plaque displaying a self-portrait of Bohnen, and etching plates. Scattered notes and writings include typescripts of speeches, plays, and poems.
Three scrapbooks of clippings and additional printed material consisting of loose clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and reproductions of artwork offer a good overview of Bohnen's career.
Photographs are primarily of Bohnen's artwork and protrait clients. Two photograph albums contain scattered photographs of Bohnen, family members, colleagues, and artwork. Other photographs are of Bohnen at his easel, family members, colleagues including sculptor Paul Dubois working in his studio, artist Grace Neal, and views of Paris. There are also photographs of Native American models in ceremonial headdresses. Photographs of clients include Sarah Bernhardt, William Jennings Bryan, Enrico Caruso, Fritz Feld, Mary Garden, and Helen Hayes, among others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series. Each series is arranged chronologically, with the exception of Series 8: Photographs.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1898-1952 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1892-1977 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Business Records, 1914-1952 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 4: Artwork, 1900-1935 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, 1917-1974 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1904-1962 (Boxes 1-2, OV 5; 15 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1907-1977 (Boxes 2, 4; 19 folders)
Series 8: Photographs, 1888-1951 (Boxes 2-4; 1 linear foot)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Bernhardt, Sarah, 1844-1923; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925; Caruso, Enrico; DuBois, Paul; Feld, Fritz, 1900-1993; Garden, Mary,1877-1967; Hayes, Helen; Neal, Grace, 1917-
Subjects-Topical:
Portrait painters -- Minnesota
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks; Works of art; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Etchings; Writings
Names:
Collier, Constance,1878-1955; Erskine, John; Ferber, Edna, 1887-1968; Kellogg, Frank B.; Marr, Carl von, 1858-1936
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1898-1952, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Biographical material includes miscellaneous Bohnen family histories and chronologies, Bohnen's marriage certificate, school transcripts, and a copy of his burial certificate.
  - Bohnen Family Histories and Chronologies, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Calling Card, Marriage Certificate, School Transcripts, and Burial Certificate, 1898-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1892-1977, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Family correspondence consists of letters exchanged between Bohnen, his wife, siblings, and children. Also included are condolence letters received by the family following Bohnen's death. General correspondence is with colleagues including Carl Von Marr, and portrait clients including Constance Collier, John Erskine, Edna Ferber, and Frank B. Kellogg.
  Family correspondence is filed chronologically before General correspondence, which is also chronological. Undated letters are filed by surname.
  - Family Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family Correspondence, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family Correspondence, 1893, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Family Correspondence, 1894-1897 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family Correspondence, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family Correspondence, 1902-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family Correspondence, 1928, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Family Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family Correspondence, 1931, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Family Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Family Correspondence, 1934, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Family Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Family Correspondence, 1936, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Family Correspondence, 1937, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Family Correspondence, 1938, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Family Correspondence, 1939, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Family Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Family Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Family Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Family Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Family Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Family Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Undated General Correspondence from Individuals with Unknown Surnames, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Undated General Correspondence from Individuals with Surnames "A"-"C," undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Undated General Correspondence from Individuals with Surnames "D"-"Z," undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - General Correspondence, 1892-1898 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - General Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - General Correspondence, 1912-1919 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - General Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - General Correspondence, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - General Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - General Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - General Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - General Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - General Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - General Correspondence, 1931, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
  - General Correspondence, 1932, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-51)
  - General Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - General Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - General Correspondence, 1935, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 54-56)
  - General Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - General Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - General Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - General Correspondence, 1940-1951 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - General Correspondence, 1952, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
  - General Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Business Records, 1914-1952, Series 3:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Business records include a contract for financing backing of artistic activities, insurance records, miscellaneous receipts, and a file concerning Bohnen's injuries on an American Airlines flight.
  - Contract for Financing Artistic Activities, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Insurance Records, 1933-1939, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 67-70)
  - File Concerning Bohnen's Accident on American Airlines, 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 71-72)
  - Miscellaneous Medical Records, 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 73-74)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1914-1935 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Artwork, 1900-1935, Series 4:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  Artwork consists of a sketchbook, miscellaneous sketches, hand-lettered signs for Bohnen's portrait business, etchings by Bohnen and others, a bronze plaque displaying a self-portrait of Bohnen, and etching plates.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Hand-Lettered Signs, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Etchings by Bohnen and Others, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Bronze Plaque Portrait of Bohnen, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Zinc Etching Plate, undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Copper Etching Plates, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 82-83)
- Notes and Writings, 1917-1974, Series 5:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  This series includes miscellaneous notes, typescripts of speeches, plays, and poems, and miscellaneous writings.
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1928-1974, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 84-85)
  - Typescript of Speech about Dr. Ridlon, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Typescript of Speech "The Statesmen of Europe Will Be Forced to Make Peace," 1917 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Typescripts of Plays, circa 1935 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Miscellaneous Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Copy of Chapter 13 of Book The Last Round Up by Harry Johnston, undated (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Miscellaneous Writings by Others, undated (Box 1, Folder 91)
- Scrapbooks, 1904-1962, Series 6:; (Boxes 1-2, OV 5; 15 folders)
  Three dismantled scrapbooks of clippings document events in Bohnen's career as a portrait painter.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1904-1962, (11 folders) (Box 1, Folder 92-102)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1913-1928, (2 folders; see also OV 5) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1914-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Pages of Scrapbook 2, 1913-1928 (Box OV 5)
- Printed Material, 1907-1977, Series 7:; (Boxes 2, 4; 19 folders)
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, reproductions of artwork, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1907-1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1952-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1921-1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Bohnen, undated, (3 folders; see also Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, 1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Booklets, 1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Reproductions of Portraits by Bohnen, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4 (sol))
- Photographs, 1888-1951, Series 8:; (Boxes 2-4; 1 linear foot)
  Photo Album 1 contains photographs of Bohnen, family members, colleagues, and scattered printed material. Photo Album 2 contains photographs of artwork. Other photographs are of Bohnen at his easel, family members, colleagues including sculptor Paul Dubois in his studio, artist Grace Neal, and views of Paris including street scenes, café scenes, and the funeral procession of General Foch. There are also photographs of Native American models in ceremonial headdresses, photographs of clients including Sarah Bernhardt, William Jennings Bryan, Enrico Caruso, Fritz Feld, Mary Garden, and Helen Hayes, and photographs of artwork.
  Photographs of Clients and the Photographs of Portraits of Clients, are arranged alphabetically.
  - Photograph Album 1, 1888-1951, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 21-25)
  - Photograph Album 2, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Photographs of Carl Bohnen, 1940, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
  - Photographs of Family Members, Colleagues, and Unidentified Individuals, 1925-1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Views of Paris, 1929-1933, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
  - Photographs of Native American Models, undated, (see also Box 3, F21) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Female Clients, 1936, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Male Clients, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41-43)
  - Photographs of Clients Miss Alexander and Mrs. Alfring, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Photographs of Clients Vicki Baum and John Golden, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Photograph of Client Sarah Bernhardt, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Photographs of Client William Jennings Bryan, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Photograph of Client Pierce Butler, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Photographs of Client Enrico Caruso, 1921, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Photographs of Clients Mrs. Clark, Dr. Cook, and William Cosgrave, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Photographs of Clients Mrs. Cunningham and Her Daughter, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Photographs of Client Fritz Feld, 1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Photographs of Clients Miner Gallup and Mary Garden, 1912-1924, (see also Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Photographs of Client Helen Hayes, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Photographs of Client Miss Hope, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Photographs of Clients Ferdinand Inetz, Isabel Irving, and Edward Johnson, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Photographs of Client Frank B. Kellogg, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Photographs of Client Mrs. Kenney, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Photographs of Clients the S. F. King Family, 1937, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 59-62)
  - Photographs of Clients Andrews Lang and Anton Lang, 1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Photographs of Clients Mr. and Mrs. Little, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Photographs of Clients Mr. Miranda, Miss Marlow, Riccardo Martin, Mr. Mather, John McCutcheon, Frank McNally, and Cardinal Mundelein, 1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Photographs of Client Governor Floyd Olson, 1930-1933 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Photographs of Clients Mrs. Mulroony Olson and L. P. Ordway, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Photographs of Clients Mildred Potter, Francis Reitz, and Mr. and Miss Shimoneck, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Photographs of Client Ernestine Schumann-Heink, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Photographs of Clients Dr. Wieland, Benno Ziegler, and L. Ziegler, 1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Portraits, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Photographs of Portraits of Unidentified Women, undated, (5 folders; see also Box 3, F22) (Box 2, Folder 72-76)
  - Photographs of Portraits of Unidentified Men, undated, (5 folders; see also Box 3, F23) (Box 2, Folder 77-81)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "A," undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "B," undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "C," undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "D," undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "E," undated, (see also Box 4 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "F," undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "G," 1912, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 88-89)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "H," 1942, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 90-91)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "I"-"J," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "K," 1937, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "L," undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 4-5)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "M," undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 6-7)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "N," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "O," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "P," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "R," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "S," undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 12-13)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "T," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Portraits with Client Surnames "W," undated (Box 3 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Artwork, undated, (5 folders; see also Box 3, F24) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 16-20)
  - Glass Plate Negatives of Native American Models, undated, (see also Box 2, F27) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 21)
  - Glass Plate Negatives of Portraits of Unidentified Woman, undated, (see also Box 3, F72-76) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Glass Plate Negatives of Portraits of unidentified Men, undated, (see also Box 3, F77-81) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 23)
  - Glass Plate Negatives of Miscellaneous Artwork, undated, (see also Box 3, F16-20) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 24)
  - Oversized Photographs of Mary Garden and of Edward, Prince of Wales, 1924, undated (Box 4 (sol))